<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://gourabp7.github.io//</id>
  <title><![CDATA[Gourab Panigrahi]]></title>
  <icon>https://gourabp7.github.io//favicon.png</icon>
  <link href="https://gourabp7.github.io/" />
  <link href="https://gourabp7.github.io//atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <updated>2025-04-08T14:58:38.757Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gourab Panigrahi]]></name>
  </author>
  <category term="High Performance Computing" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=High%20Performance%20Computing" />
  <category term="Matrix-Free Methods" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Matrix-Free%20Methods" />
  <category term="Large scale Eigenvalue Problems" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Large%20scale%20Eigenvalue%20Problems" />
  <category term="Finite Element Method" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Finite%20Element%20Method" />
  <category term="Density Functional Theory" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Density%20Functional%20Theory" />
  <category term="ACM Gordon Bell Prize" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=ACM%20Gordon%20Bell%20Prize" />
  <category term="DFT-FE" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=DFT-FE" />
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conferences and Talks]]></title>
    <link href="https://gourabp7.github.io//conferences" />
    <id>https://gourabp7.github.io//conferences</id>
    <published>2025-04-08T14:58:14.654Z</published>
    <updated>2025-04-08T14:58:14.654Z</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-1d6tf40"><a href="https://youtu.be/jjwo7lEF-kc?si=lPGCfKxXnrvjzGUR&t=115">SC &#39;23 Award Ceremony - ACM Gordon Bell Prize</a></p> <hr> <h1 id="conferences" data-svelte-h="svelte-1lwcq8b"><a href="#conferences">Conferences</a></h1> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-qv4eqj"><strong>Fast hardware-aware matrix-free algorithm for large-scale finite element discretized eigenvalue problems</strong> <br> <strong><em>PMRF Symposium 2025, IIT Hyderabad, India</em></strong></p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-1yp908y"><img src="/assets/pmrf_symposium.jpg"></div> <hr> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-vskqsd"><strong>Fast hardware-aware matrix-free algorithm for large-scale finite element discretized eigenvalue problems (Best Poster Award)</strong> <br> <strong><em>Indo-German Workshop on Hardware-aware Scientific Computing (IGHASC) 2024, Heidelberg, Germany</em></strong></p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-kpsly"><img src="/assets/ighasc.jpeg"></div> <hr> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-efk9q"><strong>Hardware aware matrix-free approach for accelerating finite-element discretized eigenvalue problems: Application to large-scale Kohn-Sham density functional theory</strong> <br> <strong><em>The 9th European Congress on Computational Methods in Applied Sciences and Engineering Congress (ECCOMAS) 2024, Lisbon, Portugal</em></strong></p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-9ff1z8"><img src="/assets/eccomas.jpeg"></div> <hr> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-vtawiq"><strong><em>ACM India Event 2024, NISER Bhubaneswar, India</em></strong></p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-9mrbiz"><img src="/assets/acm-india.jpg"></div> <hr> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1sh3ax5"><strong>Large-Scale Materials Modeling at Quantum Accuracy: Ab Initio Simulations of Quasicrystals and Interacting Extended Defects in Metallic Alloys</strong> <br> <strong><em>SC ‘23: Proceedings of the International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage and Analysis, Denver, USA</em></strong></p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-e6rzav"><img src="/assets/sc23.jpg"></div> <hr> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-ljpl1m"><strong>An Efficient Hardware-Aware Matrix-Free Implementation for the Finite-Element Discretized Operator Action on Multi-Component Vectors</strong> <br> <strong><em>SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering (CSE23) 2023, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</em></strong></p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-1qh9s3p"><img src="/assets/siam_cse23.jpg"></div> <hr> <h1 id="invited-talks" data-svelte-h="svelte-14aptx6"><a href="#invited-talks">Invited Talks</a></h1> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-hxu6m"><li><p><strong>Hardware aware matrix-free approach for accelerating FE discretized eigenvalue problems: Application to large-scale Kohn-Sham density functional theory</strong> <br> <strong><em>MFEM Community Workshop 2024</em></strong></p></li> <li><p><strong>An Efficient Hardware-Aware Matrix-Free Implementation on GPUs</strong> <br> <strong><em>NVIDIA GTC 2022 - CUDA Developers Session</em></strong></p></li></ul>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Publications]]></title>
    <link href="https://gourabp7.github.io//publications" />
    <id>https://gourabp7.github.io//publications</id>
    <published>2025-04-08T14:58:14.654Z</published>
    <updated>2025-04-08T14:58:14.654Z</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-131fwkx"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jpdc.2024.104925" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank"><strong>Fast hardware-aware matrix-free algorithms for higher-order finite-element discretized matrix multivector products on distributed systems</strong> <strong><em>(Panigrahi et al., 2024)</em></strong></a> <br></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-eohijk"><strong><em>(Part of the work that won the <a href="https://www.acm.org/media-center/2023/november/gordon-bell-prize-2023" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">2023 ACM Gordon Bell Prize</a>, the highest prize in High Performance Computing)</em></strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ah4vy1">Recent hardware-aware matrix-free algorithms for higher-order finite-element (FE) discretized matrix-vector multiplications reduce floating point operations and data access costs compared to traditional sparse matrix approaches. In this work, we address a critical gap in existing matrix-free implementations which are not well suited for the action of FE discretized matrices on very large number of vectors. In particular, we propose efficient matrix-free algorithms for evaluating FE discretized matrix-multivector products on both multi-node CPU and GPU architectures. To this end, we employ batched evaluation strategies, with the batchsize tailored to underlying hardware architectures, leading to better data locality and enabling further parallelization. On CPUs, we utilize even-odd decomposition, SIMD vectorization, and overlapping computation and communication strategies. On GPUs, we develop strategies to overlap compute with data movement for achieving efficient pipelining and reduced data accesses through the use of GPU-shared memory, constant memory and kernel fusion. Our implementation outperforms the baselines for Helmholtz operator action on 1024 vectors, achieving up to 1.4x improvement on one CPU node and up to 2.8x on one GPU node, while reaching up to 4.4x and 1.5x improvement on multiple nodes for CPUs (3072 cores) and GPUs (24 GPUs), respectively. We further benchmark the performance of the proposed implementation for solving a model eigenvalue problem for 1024 smallest eigenvalue-eigenvector pairs by employing the Chebyshev Filtered Subspace Iteration method, achieving up to 1.5x improvement on one CPU node and up to 2.2x on one GPU node while reaching up to 3.0x and 1.4x improvement on multi-node CPUs (3072 cores) and GPUs (24 GPUs), respectively.</p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-1655z2p"><img src="/assets/MatrixFree.png"></div>  <hr> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1fq2qb"><a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3581784.3627037" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank"><strong>Large-Scale Materials Modeling at Quantum Accuracy: Ab Initio Simulations of Quasicrystals and Interacting Extended Defects in Metallic Alloys</strong> <strong><em>(Das et al., 2023)</em></strong></a> <br></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-14urpup"><strong><em>(Winner of the <a href="https://www.acm.org/media-center/2023/november/gordon-bell-prize-2023" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">2023 ACM Gordon Bell Prize</a>, the highest prize in High Performance Computing)</em></strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-jap6h1">Ab initio electronic-structure has remained dichotomous between achievable accuracy and length-scale. Quantum many-body (QMB) methods realize quantum accuracy but fail to scale. Density functional theory (DFT) scales favorably but remains far from quantum accuracy. We present a framework that breaks this dichotomy by use of three interconnected modules: (i) invDFT: a methodological advance in inverse DFT linking QMB methods to DFT; (ii) MLXC: a machine-learned density functional trained with invDFT data, commensurate with quantum accuracy; (iii) DFT-FE-MLXC: an adaptive higher-order spectral finite-element (FE) based DFT implementation that integrates MLXC with efficient solver strategies and HPC innovations in FE-specific dense linear algebra, mixed-precision algorithms, and asynchronous compute-communication. We demonstrate a paradigm shift in DFT that not only provides an accuracy commensurate with QMB methods in ground-state energies, but also attains an unprecedented performance of 659.7 PFLOPS (43.1% peak FP64 performance) on 619,124 electrons using 8,000 GPU nodes of Frontier supercomputer.</p> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-1uikydf"><img src="/assets/quasiCrystal.png"></div>]]>
    </content>
    <category term="High Performance Computing" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=High%20Performance%20Computing" />
    <category term="Matrix-Free Methods" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Matrix-Free%20Methods" />
    <category term="Large scale Eigenvalue Problems" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Large%20scale%20Eigenvalue%20Problems" />
    <category term="Finite Element Method" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Finite%20Element%20Method" />
    <category term="Density Functional Theory" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=Density%20Functional%20Theory" />
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Workshops]]></title>
    <link href="https://gourabp7.github.io//workshops" />
    <id>https://gourabp7.github.io//workshops</id>
    <published>2025-04-08T14:58:14.654Z</published>
    <updated>2025-04-08T14:58:14.654Z</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-1nsrvt0"><b>NSM Open Hackathon 2023 organized by <i>National Supercomputing Mission (NSM), NVIDIA and SERC Department, IISc</i></b></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-17whrwo">Mentored Team Astro Accelerate to optimize their library <a href="https://github.com/AstroAccelerateOrg/astro-accelerate">Astro Accelerate</a></p> <hr> <div data-svelte-h="svelte-efbkf"><img src="/assets/fem_workshop.jpeg"></div> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-iat2l0"><b>Finite Element Workshop 2023 organized with <i>IEEE Bangalore Chapter and CeNSE Department, IISc</i></b></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1pk8r8i">Organized a workshop covering Finite Element Methods, Multiphysics Modeling and various solvers employed in these models</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[About]]></title>
    <link href="https://gourabp7.github.io//about" />
    <id>https://gourabp7.github.io//about</id>
    <published>2025-04-08T14:58:14.593Z</published>
    <updated>2025-04-08T14:58:14.593Z</updated>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p data-svelte-h="svelte-12flqga">Main Building at IISc, Bangalore</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-l9qhid">Hi, my name’s Gourab and I’m a PhD Student at the Department of Computational Data Sciences, Indian Institute of Science (IISc), Bangalore. My research focusses on developing hardware-aware computational algorithms and novel implementation procedures for accelerating large-scale eigenvalue problems on heterogenous architectures and further accelerating these problems by developing communication avoidance procedures. These problems arise in quantum modeling of materials and are solved on extreme-scaling computing architectures using finite element discretization of Kohn-Sham density functional theory equations.</p> <hr> <h2 id="education" data-svelte-h="svelte-dhxltm"><a href="#education">Education</a></h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-5486qc"><strong><em>B.Sc. (Research) in Physics (First Class)</em></strong> (2014-2018) <br> <strong>Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore</strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-ged4k3">Studied Non-Hermitian PT-Symmetric Quantum Hamiltonian models used to describe nonequilibrium steady states of dissipative quantum systems. Bachelors Thesis titled “<em>Orbital Effect of Magnetic Field on a Current Driven System</em>” under Prof. Sumilan Banerjee.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-nbhgvi"><strong><em>M.S. in Physics</em></strong> (2018-2019) <br> <strong>Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore</strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1j19j9o">Implementated a time-dependent density functional theory module in an in-house python port of quantum espresso and applying it to study the response or the induced polarization when a time-dependent electric field is applied to a system. Masters Thesis titled “<em>Time-dependent Density Functional Theory</em>” under Prof. Manish Jain.</p> <hr> <h2 id="experience" data-svelte-h="svelte-19x40l8"><a href="#experience">Experience</a></h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-113jwe7"><strong><em>Project Associate</em></strong> (2020-2021) <br> <strong>MATRIX Lab, Department of Computational Data Sciences, IISc</strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1ayp1s0">Developed hardware-aware computational algorithms based on the matrix-free paradigm to evaluate on-the-fly finite-element discretized matrix-multivector products arising in solving the DFT problem without storing the cell-level matrices or the global sparse matrix.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1we4jc4">Contributed to <a href="https://sites.google.com/umich.edu/dftfe" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank"><strong>DFT-FE</strong></a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpc.2022.108473" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank"><strong><em>(Das et al., 2022)</em></strong></a> <br> <strong><em>(Winner of the <a href="https://www.acm.org/media-center/2023/november/gordon-bell-prize-2023" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">2023 ACM Gordon Bell Prize</a>, the highest prize in High Performance Computing)</em></strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-qf9jgz">DFT-FE (C++/CUDA/MPI) is a massively parallel finite-element based open-source code for material modeling using density functional theory (DFT). DFT-FE can handle periodic, non-periodic and semi-periodic calculations. It can further handle both pseudopotential (ONCV, Troullier-Martins) and all-electron (non-relativistic) calculations; XC functionals supported are LDA, GGA (including spin-polarized); Capabilities include ground-state calculations, structural relaxations (ionic, cell), ab-initio MD (NVE). Scalability tested on ~200,000 MPI tasks on many-core architectures and ~64,000 GPUs on hybrid CPU-GPU architectures.</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1m585wf"><strong><em>KVPY Summer Project</em></strong> (May 2016 - July 2016) <br> <strong>Theoretical Condensed Matter Group, Department of Physics, IISc</strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-vgsuvh">Studied Ising model and Spin systems using Neural Networks under Prof. Tanmoy Das</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1vy1ikx"><strong><em>KVPY Summer Project</em></strong> (May 2015 - July 2015) <br> <strong>Tomography Lab, Department of Physics, IISc</strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1c2uhjw">Studied the variation in DOLP of light propagating through turbid media under Prof. Rajan Kanhirodan</p> <hr> <h2 id="honors-and-awards" data-svelte-h="svelte-8a5zwu"><a href="#honors-and-awards">Honors and Awards</a></h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-10t3ej3"><a href="https://www.acm.org/media-center/2023/november/gordon-bell-prize-2023" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank"><strong>ACM Gordon Bell Prize</strong></a> <br>Issued by ACM <strong><em>(The highest prize in High Performance Computing)</em></strong></p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-2tb32e"><strong>Prime Minister’s Research Fellowship (PMRF)</strong> <br>Issued by Ministry of Education (MoE), Government of India</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-mmvsv0"><strong>IEEE TCHPC Travel Award</strong> <br>Issued by IEEE</p> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1gtobse"><strong>Kishore Vaigyanik Protsahan Yojana Fellowship (KVPY)</strong> <br>Issued by Department of Science and Technology (DST), Government of India</p> <hr> <h2 id="skills" data-svelte-h="svelte-1blupa"><a href="#skills">Skills</a></h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-t0urfl"><code>C/C++</code>, <code>CUDA</code>, <code>HIP</code>, <code>SYCL</code>, <code>MPI</code>, <code>OpenMP</code>, <code>Python</code> and <code>Svelte</code></p> <hr> <h2 id="teaching-assistant" data-svelte-h="svelte-1baxd27"><a href="#teaching-assistant">Teaching Assistant</a></h2> <ul data-svelte-h="svelte-1rcpoa0"><li><a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLcj3Q8WAlaGy_5h0zLlP3LBTzYYtuP3yM&feature=shared" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">Programming in Modern C++ (noc25-cs58) at NPTEL (Jan 2025 - April 2025)</a></li> <li><a href="https://youtube.com/playlist?list=PLcj3Q8WAlaGwzSETKfAdW8f0A_ffsCsSE&feature=shared" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer external" target="_blank">Programming in Modern C++ (noc24-cs125) at NPTEL (July 2024 - Oct 2024)</a></li> <li>Numerical Linear Algebra (DS284) at Department of Computational and Data Sciences, IISc (Aug 2024 - Dec 2024)</li> <li>Numerical Linear Algebra (DS284) at Department of Computational and Data Sciences, IISc (Aug 2022 - Dec 2022)</li></ul>]]>
    </content>
    <category term="ACM Gordon Bell Prize" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=ACM%20Gordon%20Bell%20Prize" />
    <category term="DFT-FE" scheme="https://gourabp7.github.io//?tags=DFT-FE" />
  </entry>
</feed>